Guide to the Jesse Pyrant Andrews photographs and oral histories, 1973-2020 RL.00043
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
- Train Project, View from Amtrak Northeast Regional, Train #147, 2010; 1.0 Linear Feet 31 prints
  - [Overhead view of tree-lined tracks], 2010 Nov. 19 (Box 4, Image RL00043_P_082)
    Orig. print number: JA_LAL_108_36
  - [Worker on railroad bridge with street beyond], 2012 Mar. 23 (Box 4, Image RL00043_P_083)
    Orig. print number: JA_LAL_111_19A_20
  - [City station ramp with fence, opaque roof with arches], 2010 November 19 (Box 4, Image RL00043_P_084)
    Orig. print number: JA_LAL_109_5A
  - [Large covered train station platform with white stool], 2010 November 19 (Box 4, Image RL00043_P_085)
    Orig. print number: JA_LAL_109_14A
  - [Reflection of photographer's face on interior train window], 2010 November 19 (Box 4, Image RL00043_P_086)
    Orig. print number: JA_LAL_111_20A_21
- Virginia, 1975-2017; 4.0 Linear Feet 61 photographic prints; 23 CD-ROMs; 13.11 Gigabytes 46 audio files 23 .mp3 files; 23 .wav files
  The oral histories accompanying the prints are open to research use. As they require additional preparation time for access, please contact the Rubenstein Library before coming to use these materials.
  Comprises 61 11x14 inch black-and-white (gelatin silver) photographs scenes taken mainly in the Halifax, Virginia area; other locations include Danville, Virgilina, and Franklin and Pittsylvania Counties. Many of the portraits form part of the Carter-Wooding Project and the Veterans Project and are primarily of farmers and military veterans. Additional subjects include small business operators, townspeople, musicians, and rural farms and landscapes.
  Accompanying many of the photographs are oral history interviews conducted by Jesse Andrews. Original media disks are closed, but digital copies are open to research use; please contact the Rubenstein Library for access to these materials.
  A note from the photographer on the the Carter-Wooding project: "The Carter-Wooding project is something I started in the late 1990s, documenting the 'old Carter farm' in Halifax County, where I now live. The property was originally a 5000-acre land grant from King George, divided into five parcels and given to the five (then) Carter brothers. As was common at that time, the Woodings and Carters intermarried over several generations, thus the name. The Woodings were prominent early settlers in both Halifax and Pittsylvania Counties. The Carters were prominent Virginia settlers since the beginning. The land grant extended from the Banister river, which borders the north side of Halifax (town), northward up what is now Rt. 501. It was probably little more than a footpath then. There are two fragments of the land grant remaining, one of them being a 200 acre parcel (the old Carter farm) and another smaller parcel located about a mile north of the other. One of them is owned by a friend of mine, who is in one of the photographs in the collection, an image of him standing in the doorway of the pack barn. His father is seated on the step in front of him. His father, Robert Wooding, died in 2004, and took a great deal of history with him. His son, Robbie (my friend) still lives on the farm and still grows a little dark-fired tobacco."
  The prints are arranged in rough chronological order. Original titles, captions, and negative identifiers have been retained as assigned by Andrews.
  - Reid Carter, Chatham, Virginia, 1976 (Box 4, Image RL00043_P_087)
    Orig. print number: JA/POR 52-6
    Reid Carter was a mechanic who worked primarily on pulpwood trucks. He lived with his mother in a cabin without running water or electricity. When she died in 1982, at age 100, Reid lost his mind and was committed to a state mental institution in Staunton. He died a few months later.
  - Tattoo Red's, Danville, Virginia, 1994 (Box 4, Image RL00043_P_088)
    Orig. print number: JA/POR 87-17
    Red's was a gathering place for local outlaw bikers, the Scorpions. Red died in 2007.
  - Lily Savage, Halifax, Virginia, 2007 (Box 4, Image RL00043_P_089)
    Orig. print number: JA/LAL 97-25
  - Halifax County, Virginia, 2008 (Box 4, Image RL00043_P_090)
  - Edwin Wemple, Charlottesville, Virginia, 1976 (Box 4, Image RL00043_P_091)
    Orig. print number: JA/POR 4x5-3
    Ed Wemple grew up in Charlottesville and graduated from the University of Virginia. He wandered the country during the depression of the 1930s. He worked as a longshoreman in New York, in lumber camps in Oregon and eventually went to Mexico, where he became a heroin addict. He cured himself by walking from El Paso to the Oklahoma border. He returned to New York, where he lived until 1964, taking in the bohemian and jazz cultures and working at odd jobs. He returned to Charlottesville in 1964 and lived there until his death in 1987. I lived in the same house with him for a year. He had not had a bath in nine years and spent his time reading and sleeping. He went by taxi once a week to the Alderman Library to replenish his book supply. A wonderful man who had endless stories to tell about his life. I regret that I did not record any of our conversations.
  - Frank Joseph Wilcosky and his son, Frank Joseph Wilcosky, Jr., 2005, 2 items 1 print; 1 CD (Box 4, Image RL00043_P_092, Digital-materials RL.00043-SET-0001u, Audio-file RL00043-CD-0002.MP3)
    Orig. print number: JA/POR 146-53
    Print measures 9 7/8 x 7 7/8 inches. Accompanied by oral history recording. Part of the Carter-Wooding project.
    The oral history is open to research use. As it requires advance preparation for access, please contact the Rubenstein Library before coming to use this material.
  - Matthew Lafayette Aaron ("Fate" Aaron), 2006 September; 2 items 1 print; 1 CD (Box 4, Image RL00043_P_093, Digital-materials RL.00043-SET-0001u, Audio-file RL00043-CD-0006.MP3)
    Orig. print number: JA/POR 77-19
    Born Jan. 10, 1919 at Callands, Virginia. Grew up on a tobacco farm, enlisted in the Army in 1941, fought as an infantryman through North Africa, then as a Ranger through the Sicilian and Italian campaigns. Discharged November, 1945. Wounded three times in what he called "three years of continuous combat." As a Ranger he was usually at the forward most front of the fighting. He has suffered since his discharge with severe PTSD and alcoholism. In spite of that, as well as his physical wounds, he was a successful tobacco farmer until he retired in 1994. He lives on the same farm where he was born. Up to this time I have not been able to convince Mr. Aaron to agree to an oral history. When I made this photograph, he said, "I was a nice fellow when this picture was made (the portrait of himself he is holding), before I went overseas. Since then, I don't know, I just never have been the same." This is part of the Disabled Veterans series.
    The oral history interview with Aaron was completed in 2012.
    The oral history is open for research use. As it requires advance preparation for access, please contact the Rubenstein Library before coming to use this material.
  - Mrs. Maynard Amos, circa 2000-2006 (Box 4, Image RL00043_P_094)
    Orig. print number: JA/POR 51-35
    Mrs. Maynard Amos operated Amos' General Store at Callands, Virginia. with her husband until he suffered a stroke in 1999. Since then she has run the store on her own. One of only a handful of such rural businesses still in operation, it remains a gathering place for local farmers and a source for gasoline, farm supplies, groceries, patent medicines, and just about anything else a person might need.
  - Giles Herman Motley ("Mud" Motley), 1961-2003, near Climax, Virginia, 1998 August (Box 4, Image RL00043_P_095)
    Orig. print number: JA/POR 41-16
    Died of alcoholism, October, 2003. A close friend.
  - Giles Herman Motley at Weal, Virginia, 2002 October (Box 4, Image RL00043_P_096)
    Orig. print number: JA/POR 49-28
  - James Bianchi, sandwich maker, at the Corner Deli, Charlottesville, Virginia, 1976 September (Box 5, Image RL00043_P_097)
    Orig. print number: JA/POR 38-28
  - Rogers Royal holding a stick of cured brightleaf tobacco, near Climax, Virginia, 2000 (Box 5, Image RL00043_P_098)
    Orig. print number: JA/POR 49-19
    He is the last farmer in Pittsylvania County to cure his tobacco with wood. This is practically a lost art, having been replaced almost completely with oil and propane curing by the mid 1970s.
  - Rogers Royal sitting under a tobacco curing barn shelter at his farm, 2000 October (Box 5, Image RL00043_P_099)
    Orig. print number: JA/POR 49-22
    Born on this farm in 1930, one of sixteen children. His father was killed in a fall from a hay wagon in 1951.
  - Lawrence Van Witcher (Larry Witcher), 1950-2004, Tomahawk Mill near Climax, Virginia, 1984 July (Box 5, Image RL00043_P_100)
    Orig. print number: JA/POR 56-8LW
    Larry was the miller at this water-powered grist mill, which had been in continuous operation since the 1870s. He died in 2004 from a heart attack. A lifelong friend.
  - George Riser, Covesville, Virginia, 2005 January 1 (Box 5, Image RL00043_P_101)
  - Parlor dance, Carter farm, Halifax, Virginia, 2006 May (Box 5, Image RL00043_P_102)
    Orig. print number: JA/LAL 148-15
    Part of the Carter-Wooding project.
  - Parlor dance, Carter farm, Halifax, Virginia, 2006 May (Box 5, Image RL00043_P_103)
    Orig. print number: JA/LAL 147-10
    Musicians are Glenn Waller, Tim Peade, Ken Peade, and Robert Anderson. The child dancing is Mark Aaron. Part of the Carter-Wooding project.
  - Chatham Theater, Chatham, Virginia, 1976 (Box 5, Image RL00043_P_104)
    Orig. print number: JA/LAL 44-22
  - Storefront, Brookneal, Virginia, 2006 March (Box 5, Image RL00043_P_105)
  - Storefront, Brookneal, Virginia, 2006 March (Box 5, Image RL00043_P_106)
  - Storefront, Brookneal, Virginia, 2006 March (Box 5, Image RL00043_P_107)
  - Frank H. Andrews, Chatham, Virginia, 2004 May (Box 5, Image RL00043_P_108)
    Orig. print number: JA/LAL 100-27
    Part of the Disabled Veterans Project.
  - Farm auction, Grit, Virginia, 1976 September (Box 5, Image RL00043_P_109)
    Orig. print number: JA/SALES 7-25
    This is the McFarland farm. They had become physically unable to continue farming.
  - William Haskell Egan, Charlottesville, Virginia, 1976 (Box 5, Image RL00043_P_110)
    Orig. print number: JA/POR 4x5-15
  - Frank Joseph Wilcosky, Halifax, Virginia, 2008 August; 2 items 1 print; 1 CD (Box 7, Image RL00043_P_152, Digital-materials RL.00043-SET-0001u, Audio-file RL00043-CD-0001.MP3)
    Orig. print number: JA/POR 138-33
    Frank Joseph Wilcosky (Wil), was born December 12, 1914 to Polish immigrant parents near Latrobe, Pennsylvania. His father worked in the anthracite coal mines. Mr. Wilcosky truly lived the "rags to riches" American dream. He died in 2009, having amassed a fortune through hard work and his imaginative business sense.
    This print is accompanied by an oral history interview on two CDs.
  - Earl Link, Alton, Virginia, 2013 September (Box 7, Image RL00043_P_153)
    Orig. print number: JA/POR 151-16A
    Earl Link, a lifelong tobacco farmer, still lives on the farm where he was born in Halifax County, Virginia. He learned to play the fiddle from his uncles, who taught him the American old time fiddle style, which preceded bluegrass. In the 1940s, as bluegrass became more popular, he taught himself to play in that genre. Earl played with many bands for almost 60 years.
  - Donald Carter, Volens, Virginia, 2014 July 8; 2 items 1 print; 1 CD (Box 7, Image RL00043_P_154, Digital-materials RL.00043-SET-0001u, Audio-file RL00043-CD-0004.MP3)
    Orig. print number: JA/POR 153-28
    Donald Carter was a scout dog handler for the U.S. Army in Vietnam, 1969-1970. His dog was killed by a booby trap near the end of Carter's tour of duty. Mr. Carter is shown holding the wooden nameplate that hung on Rover's kennel.
    Part of the Veterans Series. An oral history CD accompanies this print.
    The oral history is open for research use. As it requires advance preparation for access, please contact the Rubenstein Library before coming to use these materials.
  - Don LaFlamme, Keeling, Virginia, 2014; 2 items 1 print; 1 CD (Box 7, Image RL00043_P_155, Digital-materials RL.00043-SET-0001u, Audio-file RL00043-CD-0005.MP3)
    Orig. print number: JA/POR 151-28A
    Don LaFlamme has been making custom muzzleloading rifles and pistols for over 40 years. The guns he makes are highly prized works of art as well as functional firearms.
    An oral history CD accompanies this print.
  - Clifford Kinney Rorrer, Danville, Virginia, 2015 June; 4 items 1 print; 3 CDs (Box 8, Image RL00043_P_160, Digital-materials RL.00043-SET-0001u, Audio-file RL00043-CD-0007.MP3, Audio-file RL00043-CD-0008.MP3, Audio-file RL00043-CD-0009.MP3)
    Orig. print number: JA/POR 160-9
    Kinney Rorrer is a teacher, historian, and musician. He is a well known authority on the history of "country music" and has a collection of approximately 2500 78 RPM records of early country, blues, and gospel music recorded in the 1920s and 1930s. An oral history in the form of three digital audio files accompanies this print.
  - Sam Winstead, dancing with his granddaughter at a Veterans For Peace fundraiser near Leasburg, North Carolina, 2015 June (Box 8, Image RL00043_P_161)
    Orig. print number: JA/POR 160-11
    Sam Winstead is a 93 year old Marine Corps veteran of WW 2. He fought at Peleliu and Okinawa, more than 100 days of continuous combat which the Marine Corps archives describe as the most horrific fighting in the history of the Corps. In 2007, after decades of trying to find peace within himself and forgiveness for the Japanese he fought in those battles, he founded Americans For Peace, along with its adjunct Veterans For Peace, and began an annual event called Sam's Ride for Peace. Since 2010, he and others have travelled by bicycle from Raleigh, N.C. to Washington, D.C., an annual eight day ride to promote peace in the world, stopping at schools and community centers along the way to advance their message.
  - Abandoned tobacco curing barn, Pittsylvania County, Virginia, 2015 July (Box 8, Image RL00043_P_162)
    Orig. print number: JA/LAL 150-15
    This curing barn is unusual in that it is built with a cinderblock foundation and with framed walls, as opposed to the traditional log-bodied structures that typically had foundations of field stones, with mud daubing between the logs. This barn had been covered with cement stucco, much of which has fallen off, revealing cured but badly deteriorated tobacco still hanging from the tier poles inside. The sign in front of the barn reflects the sentiments of many of the citizens of Pittsylvania County, as well as surrounding counties, in response to the efforts of Walter Coles to convince the state legislature to allow him to mine a potential 119,000,000 pound deposit of uranium that lies under his land, on the Colonial-era estate known as Coles Hill, located about fifteen miles northwest of where this barn stands.
    For additional history notes, please refer to the caption list in the box containing this print.
  - Tractor accident, Rice, Virginia, 1998 (Box 8, Image RL00043_P_163)
    Orig. print number: JA/LAL 83-9
    Mary Lou Wood waits with her son, "Little Man" to learn the fate of her husband, Doug Wood, after he turned over a huge tractor while bush-hogging on an embankment a few minutes earlier. The owner of the dairy farm on which the Woods worked as tenants was on his way to the scene of the accident. Miraculously, Doug Wood was not seriously injured but the tractor was badly damaged. Farming is dangerous business. The Woods family left Rice for West Virginia soon after this event took place.
  - Abandoned satellite dish, Shooting Creek Road, Franklin County, Virginia, 2015 May (Box 8, Image RL00043_P_164)
    Orig. print number: JA/LAL 150-17
    Franklin County, Virginia, has long enjoyed the dubious, albeit somewhat romantic reputation as the "moonshine capitol of the world." Franklin County is where the now fabled "moonshine conspiracy" took place in the 1930s, the subject of Dr. Charles Thompson's book Spirits of Just Men. During that time almost everyone in the county was involved in one way or another in the production of white liquor, everyone from the county sheriff all the way down to small children, who often acted as lookouts and laborers at the numerous stills that dotted the mountainsides, well hidden in the rhododendron and mountain laurel groves. Shooting Creek Road (State Route 860) was where many of the stills were located, and runs for several miles between Rocky Mount, the county seat of Franklin County, and Floyd County, located to the west.
  - Mrs. Inez Young and her grandson, Tony Young, Virgilina, Virginia, 2015 January; 2 items 1 print; 1 CD (Box 8, Image RL00043_P_165, Digital-materials RL.00043-SET-0001u, Audio-file RL00043-CD-00012.MP3)
    Orig. print number: JA/POR 157-11
    Mrs. Young had recently celebrated her 97th birthday. She was still living by herself and "keeping house" when this photograph was made. An oral history accompanies this print.
  - Sam Thompson, Halifax, Virginia, 2015 February; 2 items 1 print; 1 CD (Box 8, Image RL00043_P_166, Digital-materials RL.00043-SET-0001u, Audio-file RL00043-CD-0013.MP3)
    Orig. print number: JA/POR 157-31
    Sam Thompson can make anything out of wood. He has been a woodworker since high school, and his work encompasses every style, from simple cabinetry to the most ornate Williamsburg reproductions. This is a part of the Halifax project. An oral history accompanies this print.
  - Steven Schopen, Halifax, Virginia, 2015 December; 2 items 1 print; 1 CD (Box 8, Image RL00043_P_168, Digital-materials RL.00043-SET-0001u, Audio-file RL00043-CD-0014.MP3)
    Orig. print number: JA/POR 162-11
    Chef Steve Schopen opened the Molasses Grill restaurant in Halifax in 2005, and has had ten very successful years as owner and head chef of that business. Born in Kent, England, in 1957, Steve has cooked all over the world. Schooled in the classic French style, he went on to learn many different styles of cooking at the restaurants in which he worked as a cook, finally earning the title "Chef" after coming to the United States in 1983. This is part of the Halifax project. An oral history accompanies this print.
  - Mildred and George Christo, Danville, Virginia, 1978 (Box 8, Image RL00043_P_169)
    Orig. print number: JA/POR 38-19
    Mildred and George Christo operated the Busy Bee Café in the Schoolfield district of Danville, Virginia until its closing in 1993. The Busy Bee was first opened in 1912 by Mildred's uncle Gus James, an immigrant from Cyprus who became an American citizen.
  - Bill and Darnell Abbott, Halifax, Virginia, 2016, 2 items 1 print; 1 CD (Box 8, Image RL00043_P_170, Digital-materials RL.00043-SET-0001u, Audio-file RL00043-CD-0010.MP3)
    Orig. print number: JA/POR 163-15
    Owners and operators of Abbott Farm Supply in Halifax, Virginia. since 1980. An oral history accompanies this print. Part of the Halifax project.
  - Herman Martin, Danville, Virginia, 2016 January (Box 8, Image RL00043_P_171)
    Orig. print number: JA/POR 163-18
    Mr. Martin celebrated his 90th birthday February 3 of 2016. Born in the Calloway community of Franklin County, Virginia, he moved to Danville, Virginia, at age 15 to work in the Dan River Cotton Mill. He lost his right arm in a hunting accident when he was 16, but continued to work at Dan River until his retirement in 1990. Before losing his arm he had been an accomplished guitar player, playing what is now referred to as "American old time music." After the accident, he learned to play the same tunes on harmonica, and continues to play three or four times a week with friends. He knows many of the old fiddle tunes and has a wonderful musical style, sometimes playing two harmonicas at one time to accommodate key changes in a particular tune.
  - Floyd Sutphin, South Boston, Virginia, 2016 August; 3 items 1 print; 2 CDs (Box 10, Image RL00043_P_172, Digital-materials RL.00043-SET-0001u, Audio-file RL00043-CD-0016.MP3, Audio-file RL00043-CD-0017.MP3)
    Orig. print number: JA/POR 166-13
    At age fourteen, Floyd Sutphin left the farm near South Boston, Virginia, where he was born, and migrated to Atlantic City, New Jersey, where he got work in the kitchen of a large hotel. At sixteen, he moved to Manhattan and settled in Harlem, where he again worked in a hotel kitchen. At eighteen, he and a partner opened the DeLuxe Barbeque Restaurant on 146th St. at 7th Ave. He operated that business for twenty years before moving back to South Boston to care for his elderly parents. Oral history accompanies this print.
  - Stewart Werner, Halifax County, Virginia, 2006 September (Box 10, Image RL00043_P_173)
    Orig. print number: JA/POR 119-13
    Stewart is a close friend and a wonderful musician. His intuitive and interpretive playing sets him apart from other banjo players. He is also a virtuoso guitarist. Stewart is currently playing with the Harwell-Grice band.
  - John Baker Wilcosky (Jack), Halifax County, Virginia, 2016 February (Box 10, Image RL00043_P_174)
    Orig. print number: JA/POR 164-5
    Jack is the older brother of Joe and Tim Wilcosky and second son of Frank Joseph Wilcosky (see his portrait and oral histories in the collection). Oral history accompanies this print.
  - Mike Vaughn and Jessica South, Ringgold, Virginia, 2016 August; 4 items 1 print; 3 CDs (Box 10, Image RL00043_P_177, Digital-materials RL.00043-SET-0001u, Audio-file RL00043-CD-0018.MP3, Audio-file RL00043-CD-0019.MP3, Audio-file RL00043-CD-0020.MP3)
    Orig. print number: JA/POR 165-15
    Mike and Jessica have owned and operated Blue Moon Tattoo and Piercing for the past sixteen years. Oral history accompanies this print.
  - Kenneth Hawks, Halifax, Virginia, 2016 July (Box 10, Image RL00043_P_178)
    Orig. print number: JA/POR 165-20
    Kenneth Hawks is owner and operator of the Guns and Stuff gun store in Halifax.
  - Robert Wooding cutting tobacco plants for spiking, 2014 September (Box 10, Image RL00043_P_179)
    Orig. print number: JA/LAL 123-16
    Robbie still grows "dark-fired" tobacco, a variety called Lizard Tail. Unlike flue-cured tobacco (Brightleaf), which is harvested leaf by leaf, dark-fired tobacco plants are cut low to the ground and the entire plant impaled on a standard tobacco stick, several plants to a stick. The sticks are then hung on the tier poles of the curing barn, just as with flue-cured tobacco. Once the barn is full, several small, smoldering fires are built on the interior dirt floor and the barn is shut up as tightly as possible. Robbie makes these fires of hickory and cedar wood. The heat and smoke from these fires dries and flavors the tobacco, a three or four day process. The result is dark-colored leaves and a strong smoky taste when the tobacco is smoked or chewed. Robbie sells some of his crop and sets aside a portion for his own use. Dark-fired tobacco has become less and less common since the industrialization of tobacco farming in the 1990s.
  - Danny Newton loading sticks of Lizard Tail tobacco onto the truck for transport to the curing barn, Halifax County, Virginia, 2014 September (Box 10, Image RL00043_P_180)
    Orig. print number: JA/LAL 114-36
    Danny is Robert Wooding's brother-in-law, married to Robbie's younger sister, Susan, who is handing Danny the sticks. Danny raises Bright Leaf tobacco and cattle near Nelson, Virginia. I have never seen Danny in a bad humor.
  - Interior of curing barn, old Carter farm, Halifax County, Virginia, 2014 September (Box 10, Image RL00043_P_181)
    Original print number: JA/LAL 115-14